Guide to the James Omura personal archive M2294
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James Omura personal archive
1912-1995
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Omura, James Matsumoto, 1912-1994
M2294
30.55 Linear Feet (58 manuscript boxes, 1 half box, 9 flat boxes, 1 map folder)
The James M. Omura Papers, 1912-1994, represent the life work of this influential Japanese American writer, journalist, and civil rights activist. Born on Bainbridge Island, Washington, in 1912, Omura worked during the 1920s and early 1930s as a laborer, until securing an editorial position with a Japanese American newspaper in Los Angeles. In 1940, Omura started up his own magazine, Current Life, which he and his wife Caryl edited until it folded during World War II. Omura became known at this time for his vociferous opposition to the forced relocation of Japanese Americans, outspoken denouncement of the Japanese American Citizens League, and editorial support of the Japanese American draft resisters. After the war, Omura left journalism to develop a successful landscaping business in Denver. He reemerged in the 1980s to participate in commemorative events relating to the evacuation and resistance movements. Given the depth and breadth of the collection, the James M. Omura Papers document the varied and dramatic history of Japanese Americans in the 20th century.
Custodial History
After James Omura’s death in 1994, the Omura family asked Professor Arthur A. Hansen to complete Omura’s unfinished memoir. The Omura papers, along with Omura’s draft manuscript, were turned over to Dr. Hansen in June 1995. They were housed in the Oral History Program Archives at California State University, Fullerton, until the memoir was completed. The collection was then donated to Stanford University.
Biographical / Historical
James Matsumoto Omura was born Utaka Matsumoto on November 27, 1912, on Bainbridge Island, Washington. His father had immigrated illegally to escape conscription into the Japanese army and had assumed the name Matsumoto to avoid detection. James Omura grew up in the small town of Winslow, across the Puget Sound from Seattle. He dropped out of school at thirteen in search of adventure in Alaska, where he found employment in the salmon canneries. From 1926 to 1929, Omura worked in the canneries, sawmills, and on the railroads in various western states before returning to Seattle. After trying unsuccessfully to get work as a reporter on the Japanese American Courier, Omura returned to school and earned his high school diploma. After graduation, Omura moved south to Los Angeles in 1933, where he took a job as the English-language editor of the Shin-Nichibei [New Japanese American News]. Three years later, he headed north and was offered a position in San Francisco as the English-language editor of the Shin Sekai Shimbun [New World Daily News]. During his tenure at that paper, some of his editorials evidently gave offense to the leaders of the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL). Omura found himself shunned by certain members of San Francisco’s Issei community, and this situation foreshadowed his chilly relations with JACL members in the 1940s and beyond. Soon after the paper merged with the Hokubei Asahi to become the Shin Sekai-Asahi Shimbun [New World Sun], Omura quit his job and began another long stretch of temporary positions, including stints as a migrant farm worker, tractor operator, and warehouse worker in central and northern California. By 1940, Omura has saved sufficient funds to launch his own magazine Current Life. After marrying and settling down in San Francisco, Omura and his first wife Caryl worked together to produce the magazine, which focused on social issues and cultural affairs of interest to the Nikkei [Japanese American] community. Following the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor, Omura attracted public attention during February 1942 by his testimony at the Tolan Committee hearings in San Francisco. Not only was he the sole Japanese American not affiliated with the JACL to testify at these hearings related to the mass eviction of Nikkei from the West Coast, but the only spokesman who protested this public policy. In March 1942 Jimmie and Caryl relocated to the “free zone” state of Colorado and there tried unsuccessfully to continue publishing Current Life. After the magazine folded, Omura opened an employment agency to assist other Japanese Americans who had voluntarily relocated in Denver and other Rocky Mountain communities. Although he had been unable to prevent the relocation process, Omura continued to speak out on behalf of other Japanese Americans, most notably for those who resisted the government’s plan in early 1944 to draft Nisei from the camps. As English editor of the Denver-based Rocky Shimpo, Omura wrote a series of controversial editorials supporting the stand of the draft resisters within the Heart Mountain Fair Play Committee. As a result of his strong public pronouncements, Omura was brought to trial for conspiring with the FPC leadership to aid and abet the violation of the Selective Service Act. Unlike his convicted co-defendants, however, Omura was exonerated on the constitutional grounds of freedom of the press. In the post-World War II years, Omura received little attention for his efforts to preserve the civil rights of Japanese Americans. Living in obscurity and relative isolation from the Japanese American community, Omura supported himself as a landscape gardener in Denver, Colorado. During the 1980s when the push for redress and reparations for Japanese American camp survivors was brought to national awareness, Omura reemerged as a writer and significant resource for those interested in the wartime resistance movement. Omura received a Lifetime Achievement Award from the Asian American Journalists Association in 1989 in recognition of his commitment to free speech in the crucible of war. Omura continued to receive honors bestowed by other organizations recognizing his courageous efforts in support of Nisei draft resistance and respect for individual conscience during World War II. He was engaged in writing his memoir at the time of his death on June 20, 1994.
Sources Hansen, Arthur A., “James Matsumoto Omura: An Interview,” Amerasia Journal 13 (2, 1986-1987): 99 -113 _________. “The 1944 Nisei Draft at Heart Mountain, Wyoming: Its Relationship to the Historical Representation of the World War II Japanese American Evacuation,” OAH Magazine (Summer 1996): 48-60. Hirose, Stacey, “James Matsumoto Omura,” in Niiya, Brian, ed., Encyclopedia of Japanese American History: An A-to-Z Reference from 1868 to the Present (New York and Los Angeles: Facts on File, Inc. and the Japanese American National Museum, 2000), 326. Omura, James, “Japanese American Journalism During World War II,” in Nomura, Gail M. et al., eds., Frontiers of Asian American Studies: Writing, Research, and Commentary (Pullman, WA: 1989), 71-80. David K. Yoo, “Insiders on the Outside: Nisei Journalists and Wartime Editorials,” Chapter 5 of Growing Up Nisei: Race, Generation, and Culture among Japanese Americans of California, 1924-49 (Urbana, IL: University of Illinois Press, 2000), 124-48.
Biographical / Historical
James Matsumoto Omura (1912-1994) was a Japanese American editor and publisher. He founded the San Francisco-based publication Current Life in 1940 and later edited the Rocky Shimpo newspaper in Denver, Colorado. Omura was politically active and was an outspoken critic of the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II.
Related Materials
The James M. Omura Papers, 1912-1994, represent the life work of this influential Japanese American writer, journalist, and civil rights activist. Born on Bainbridge Island, Washington, in 1912, Omura worked during the 1920s and early 1930s as a laborer, until securing an editorial position with a Japanese American newspaper in Los Angeles. After moving to San Francisco in 1934, Omura served as the English editor of two Japanese American newspapers and also worked as a florist. In 1940, Omura started up his own magazine, Current Life, which he and his wife Caryl edited until it folded during World War II. Omura became known at this time for his vociferous opposition to the enforced mass eviction and detention of Japanese Americans, outspoken denouncement of the Japanese American Citizens League, and editorial support of the Japanese American draft resisters. After the war, Omura left journalism to develop a successful landscaping business in Denver. He reemerged in the early 1980s to participate in the movement for Japanese American redress and reparations, to redeem the tarnished reputations on the Heart Mountain draft resisters and himself, and to prepare his memoir for publication. Given the depth and breadth of the collection, the James M. Omura Papers document the varied and dramatic history of Japanese Americans in the 20th century. The Omura Papers contain a wide variety of materials relating to his childhood, early jobs as a cannery and railroad worker, and editorial work for Japanese American newspapers. Omura preserved copies of many of his editorials and other writings, as well as his efforts to write fiction and poetry. Omura’s Current Life files are particularly valuable, including complete issues, correspondence, and article submissions. Omura was a prolific letter-writer, and he conscientiously retained copies of incoming and outgoing correspondence with his family, friends, scholars, and members of the Japanese American community. He also was a lifelong diary keeper, and these invaluable documents record his experiences and emotions during the harrowing days of the evacuation and his removal to Denver, as well as the breakup of his first marriage and ultimate bankruptcy. After Omura retired from his landscaping business and became increasingly involved in Japanese American organizations and events, he began collecting documents relating redress, reparations and other ethnic and civil rights concerns. He also accumulated extensive subject files while doing background research for his unpublished autobiography, “Shattered Lives.” Omura’s massive collection of notes and many chapter drafts for his memoir comprise an important part of this collection.
The collection was first organized into nine series: Series 1. Correspondence, 1933-1994, 3.3 linear feet Series 2. Speeches & Writings, 1924-1994, 5.2 linear feet, 6 scrapbooks Series 3. Biographical Material, 1940-1994, 0.4 linear feet Series 4. Personal Financial Records, 1937-1993, 0.2 linear feet Series 5. Personal Legal Records, 1912-1993, 0.2 linear feet Series 6. Omura Landscape Service Records, 1942-1988, 0.2 linear feet, 3 items Series 7. Audiovisual Materials, ca. 1920s-1995, 0.8 linear feet, 5 items Series 8. Ephemera & Memorabilia, 1930-1994, 0.7 linear feet Series 9. Research Material, 1930-1994, 8.7 linear feet Two additional series were subsequently added as donations. Series 10. Michi Nishiura Weglyn and Aiko Herzig Yoshinaga Correspondence and Documents. Series 11. Wayne Omura's Collection of James Omura's Personal Archive.
General
The original container listing is in Box 1, Folder 0. Minor changes were made while creating the online finding aid which supercedes the original container listing.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audiovisual materials are not available in original format, but have beeen reformatted to a digital use copy.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was given (with the family's permission) by Professor Emeritus Art Hansen of Cal-State Fullerton to Stanford University, Special Collections in December 2014.
Scope and Contents
Materials include correspondence, notes and writing for Current Life and Rocky Shimpo, clippings, biographical documents, legal and financial records, photographs, cassettes, video recordings, computer disks, government documents related to Omura, ephemera, and more.
Japanese Americans -- History; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Omura, James Matsumoto, 1912-1994; Weglyn, Michi, 1926-; Yoshinaga-Herzig, Aiko; Japanese American Citizens' League.
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1933-1994
  Japanese Americans -- History
  - A-Co, including Frank Abe, Frank Chin (Box 1, Folder 1-67)
  - Cr - Ha, including Roger Daniels, Richard Drinnon, Frank Emi, Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 2, Folder 1-62)
  - Ha - Hu, including Arthur Hansen, John Herzig, William Hohri from National Council of Japanese American Redress (Box 3, Folder 1-36)
  - I - Ko, including Toyo Suyemoto Kawakami, Mits Koshiyama, Nelson & Taka Kitsuse (Box 4, Folder 1-65)
  - Ko - Ma, including Kazushi (Casey) Matsumoto, James Omura’s Brother, Toshio Mori (Box 5, Folder 1-41)
  - M - Ok, including Paul Nakadate, Kiyoshi Okamoto (Box 6, Folder 1-61)
  - Ok - Pa, including Paul T. & Alice Nakadate, George Nazawa, Pacific Coast Evacuee Placement Bureau (Box 7, Folder 1-41)
  - Pa - Ta, including Kozie Sakai, Eddie & Doris Sato, Sumi Seki, Tokutano N. Slocum (Box 8, Folder 1-83)
  - Ta - Wr, including Toda, Tetsuko Toda, Publisher Rocky Shimpo, Mary Tomita, United States Department of the Army, Michi & Walter Weglyn (Box 9, Folder 1-65)
  - Ya - Za (Box 10, Folder 1-20)
- Series 2. Speeches & Writings, 1924-1994
  - Series 2.1. Current Life
    - Articles, clippings, correspondence, submissions and copies of complete magazine, bulk; Box 10, folder 23 houses Grass by Arthur T. Morimitsu. The document was cleaned by conservation but is quite fragile. (Box 10, Folder 21-37, Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - Series 2.2. Diaries
    - Fumiko Okuma, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
    - Holographic and typescript, 1931-1994 (Box 11, Folder 7-12)
    - Diaries - typescript - chronologies, 1912-1950 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Diaries - typescript - excerpts, incident (Box 11, Folder 13-14)
  - Series 2.3. Editorials and Columns
    - Clippings, photocopies and typescripts, 1934-1994 (Box 11, Folder 22, Box 12)
    - Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, 1930's and 1940's, Albums are unbound, fragile, deteriorating, with failing adhesives and some loose additional clippings within the pages. (Flat-box 60-62)
  - Series 2.4. Letters to the Editor
    - Typescript and/or published in Asian Week, The Call Bulletin, Chronicles Magazine, The Denver Post, 1943-1981 (Box 12, Folder 1-29)
  - Series 2.5. Manuscript Drafts
    - Fair Play Committee (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
    - Shattered Lives (Box 14-17)
    - Duplicates - typescript (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Series 2.6. Notes
    - Various, most undated (Box 17, Folder 4-16, Box 18, Folder 1-7)
    - Notes – Akutsu, Jim A. (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Notes – American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Notes - A (Box 18, Folder 9-14)
    - Notes - B-C (Box 18, Folder 15-32)
    - Notes – Congress (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - Notes – court cases (Box 18, Folder 31)
    - Notes – Drinnon, Richard (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Notes - D-E (Box 19, Folder 1-10)
    - Notes – Emi, Frank (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Notes – Esq.: Collins, Wayne (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Notes – F.B.I. Files (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Notes - F-H (Box 19, Folder 11-35)
    - Notes – Hosokawa, William (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Notes - Ito, Kazuo (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Notes – Japanese American Citizen’s League (JACL) (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Notes - I-J (Box 20, Folder 3-18)
    - Notes - K-L (Box 20, Folder 19-23, Box 21, Folder 1-10)
    - Notes – Masaoka, Mike M. (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Notes – Military – Japanese Americans (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Notes - M (Box 21, Folder 12-19)
    - Notes – Notebook Title: “Background of Evacuation; DOJ Internment Camps” (Box 21, Folder 26)
    - Notes - N (Box 21, Folder 20-32)
    - Notes – Omura, James M (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Notes - O-R (Box 21, Folder 33-34, Box 22, Folder 1-22)
    - Notes – Relocation Centers (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Notes - S-Y (Box 22, Folder 23-49, Box 23, Folder 1-9)
  - Series 2.7. Poetry
    - Several typescript or clipping of poem published in newspaper (Box 23, Folder 10-11)
  - Series 2.8. Reports
    - Treatment of Federal Prisoners of Japanese Descent, 1944 (Box 23, Folder 12-13)
  - Series 2.9. Reviews
    - Clipping - “JACL in Quest of Justice” by Bill Hosokawa (Box 23, Folder 14,16)
    - Reviews – Off Print - “Justice at War” by Peter Irons (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Reviews - Typescript - “Japanese American History” by Japanese American National Museum (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Reviews - Typescript - “Keeper of Concentration Camps: Dillon S. Myer and American Racism” by Richard Drinnon (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Reviews – Typescript – Lim Report – Correspondence and comments (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Reviews - Typescript - “They Call Me Moses Masaoka” by Mike Masaoka with Bill Hosokawa (Box 23, Folder 20)
  - Series 2.10. Short Stories
    - “Short Story Writing” (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Clavell Short Story Contest (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - Series 2.11. Speeches
    - “The Fair Play Committee Papers”, 1993 (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - “Introduction of Frank Seishi Emi”, 1994 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - “Japanese American Journalism During World War II", 1988 (Box 23, Folder 25-27)
    - “Nikkei History and its Myths” (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Notes (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - “A Rare Ethnic Honor”, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - “Seattle Hearing, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - “Why I Oppose the J.A.C.L.”, 1943 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Series 2.12. Testimony
    - Testimony – Commission on Wartime Relocation & Internment of Civilians – [Donated by Aiko Herzig, 15 May 2001], 1981 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Testimony – National Defense Migration - San Francisco Hearings [1942?] (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Series 2.13. Writers Institute Aptitude Test
    - Writers Institute Aptitude Test (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Series 3. Biographical Material, 1990-1994
  - Autobiographical Timelines (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Clippings (Box 24, Folder 10-21)
  - Clippings, Caryl Fumiko Omura (Okuma), 1941-1942 (Box 24, Folder 22)
  - Conference - “Coming of Age in the Thirties: The Nisei and the Japanese Immigrant Press”, 1944 (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - Curriculum Vitae, James Matsumoto Omura (Box 24, Folder 24)
  - Honors and Awards (Box 24, Folder 25-27)
  - Interviews (Box 24, Folder 28-31, Box 25, Folder 1-4)
  - Notes (Box 25, Folder 5-6)
  - Press Releases (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Writings about James Omura (Box 25, Folder 8-9)
- Series 4. Personal Financial Records, 1937-1993
  - Bank statements, checks, correspondence, household expenses (Box 25, Folder 1-14)
  - Ledger, notes, pay stubs, receipts, savings passbooks, W-2 forms, and other similar (Box 25, Folder 15-29)
- Series 5. Personal Legal Records, bulk
  - Agreement between New Japanese American News and Jimmy Omura, 1934 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  - Application to transfer printing contract of Current Life, 1941 (Box 25, Folder 31)
  - Bankrupt required to attend, 1945 (Box 25, Folder 32)
  - Birth certificate - copy, 1912 (Box 25, Folder 33)
  - District Court of the United States, indictment for violation of the Selective training and Service Act of 1940 - copy, 1944 (Box 25, Folder 34)
  - Name change filed in district court, 1943; complaint for divorce, 1947 (Box 25, Folder 35-36)
  - Constitution and by-laws, Denver Metropolitan Council on Fair Employment Practice (Box 25, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence with various attorneys (Box 25, Folder 38-41, Box 26, Folder 1-7)
  - Correspondence – U. S. Department of Labor, Re: Western Wholesale Florist, 1942 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Deposition F.B.I. Agent Robert Lawrence, 1944 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Driver’s License (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - “Failure of Defense Counsel to Properly Prepare Case” and “Why I Should Have Been Discharged Even Without an Attorney” (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - F.B.I. Inventory Items Seized, 1944 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Fishing License, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Motion to Quash; Motion for Bill or Particulars; Demurrer (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Report on the Coca Cola Situation, 1942 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Report: The United States vs James M. Omura, 1944 (Box 26, Folder 16-17)
  - Settlement with VJI Barbershop; Shiegeri Fujii v. United States of America; Summons Complaint for Divorce; Synopsis of Minoru Yasui's Threat of Libel Action (Box 26, Folder 18-21)
  - Warranty Deed, 1966 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - Will, 1981-05-21 (Box 26, Folder 23)
- Series 6. Omura Landscape Service, 1942-1988
  - Material related to Associated Landscape Contractors of America, Inc. (ALCA) (Box 26, Folder 24-33)
  - Advertisements, certificates, clippings (Box 26, Folder 34-36)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1980 (Box 26, Folder 37)
  - Directory of Landscape Firms, 1968 (Box 26, Folder 38)
  - Ephemera, including postcards, stationery, auction flyers, accounting statement forms (Box 26, Folder 39-45)
  - Financial records (Box 27, Folder 1-4)
  - Landscape Contractors of Colorado - memorabilia and newsletters (Box 27, Folder 5, Flatbox-small 64)
  - Landscape Plans (Box 27, Folder 6, Map-folder 65)
  - Legal works (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Memorabilia (Box 27, Folder 8, Flatbox-small 64)
  - Periodicals (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Photographs – photocopies (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Standard Army Automated Contracting System Vendor Application (Box 27, Folder 11)
- Series 7. Audio-Visual Materials, 1920-1995
  - Subseries 7.1. Photographs
    - Alaska (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Angel Island, California (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Asparagus harvest, Sacramento, California (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Association of Contractors of America (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Auto Accident, 1993 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Bowling Team, 1962-1964 (Box 27)
    - Boxer, unidentified (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Building site – unidentified; building site and equipment (Box 27, Folder 20-21)
    - Calendar photo reprints – San Francisco, 1939 (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - Collins, Wayne – attorney (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Current Life photos (Box 27, Folder 24)
    - Drinnon, Richard, 1987 (Box 27, Folder 25)
    - Fair Play Committee Poster, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 26)
    - Friends and Associates, 1931-1937 (Box 27, Folder 27)
    - “The Future” Bainbridge Island, Washington, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 28)
    - Garden Party, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 29)
    - Hidden Inlet, Alaska – negatives, 1930's (Box 27, Folder 30)
    - Home and Garden Show, 1970 (Box 27, Folder 31)
    - Horse and 2 people (Box 27, Folder 32)
    - Japanese Camp – Union Bay, Idaho, 1931 (Box 27, Folder 33)
    - Japanese Community Cultural Center – Nisei Week Queen, 1993 (Box 27, Folder 34)
    - Ketchikan, Alaska [?] – negatives (Box 27, Folder 35)
    - Kikuchi, Yuriko – New York, [1940's ?] (Box 27, Folder 36)
    - King Dome – Seattle, Washington, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 37)
    - Landscapes (Box 28, Folder 1-7)
    - Lucayan, G. B. Gardens (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Matsumoto, Casey (brother) (Box 28, Folder 9-12)
    - Miyatake, Toyo (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - National Coalition for Redress/Reparations – Day of Remembrance, 1944 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - N.C.J.A.R., Vacation & Family [1983?] (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Omura, Caryl Fumiko Okuma (Box 28, Folder 16-17)
    - Omura Family & Friends (Box 28, Folder 18-19)
    - Omura, James Matsumoto – portraits (Box 28, Folder 20-24)
    - Omura, James Matsumoto – Pocatella, Idaho; Dallas, Texas; Denver, Colorado; [Seattle, Washington] (Box 28, Folder 25-28)
    - Omura, James & Caryl (Box 28, Folder 29-30)
    - Omura, James & Koshiyama, Mits – San Jose, California (Box 28, Folder 31)
    - Negatives – James M. Omura (Box 28, Folder 32)
    - Negatives – unidentified (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
    - Omura Landscape Service (Box 29, Folder 3-19)
    - Pacific Coast Evacuee Placement Bureau (Box 29, Folder 20-21)
    - Photograph albums (Box 29, Folder 22-24)